So we started דף כ"ב. Daf Chaf Bais.
Yesterday we had a fascinating discussion more about definitions of נבילה neveilah
and death
even when the body was still somewhat functioning, which was fascinating for
contemporary issues around definitions of death. And now recently we've been discussing
the difference between a חטאת העוף chatas ha-of and an עולת העוף
olas ha-of in that a חטאת העוף, chatas ha-of, both of them
you do מליקה melikah from the back which was the discussion of
our משנה, mishnah, but a חטאת העוף chatas ha-of the תורה Torah
says ולא יבדיל, ve-lo yavdil, you do not fully separate and an
עולת העוף olas ha-of you do separate. The question is how much
do you separate? So there's the position of the תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma and רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael that says that you separate the
two סימנים simanim fully, but you don't actually have to cut the
actual skin itself. And the position of רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi
Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon that says you don't even, you only do the
majority of the two סימנים. simanim. What's the reason? The reason to
separate is because the תורה Torah says ומלק והקטיר, u-malak ve-hiktir, you
shall do מליקה melikah and burn. And we learn from another place
that you burn the head and the body separately. So the assumption
is you'll do the מליקה melikah the same way you do the
burning. The other position says no, it's similar to more of a
חטאת העוף chatas ha-of in the same way a חטאת העוף chatas
ha-of there's more connected and when you hold onto the body you're
still when you still hold onto the head the body is still
connected. So even an עולת העוף, olas ha-of, even though you do
separate both סימנים, simanim, there's still more connected. So therefore you don't
fully separate the two סימנים. simanim. So that is the discussion here.
So let's take a look where now the גמרא Gemara goes.
So now,
let's take a look at, let's actually pick up from the two
lines from the top of the גמרא. Gemara. מאי קאמר mai ka-amar
says the גמרא. Gemara. This is going on the position of רבי
אלעזר ברבי שמעון, Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon, two lines from the top
of כ"ב עמוד א'. Chaf Bais Amud Aleph. What does he mean
when he says that the חטאת העוף chatas ha-of it's the body
and the head together?
You said two dots?
No, two lines from the top. הכי קאמר. hachi ka-amar. This is
what he means. הכי קאמר, hachi ka-amar, מה להלן כשהוא אוחז הראש
בגוף מזה, mah lehalan keshe-hu ochez ha-rosh ba-guf mazeh,
the same way
so when he holds the head through either,
it's a question exactly how you read this, but either when he
holds the head he squirts the blood with the body or כשהוא
אוחז הראש בגוף keshe-hu ochez ha-rosh ba-guf when he holds the head
via the body. But basically it means that the head and the
body are still connected when he is doing the squirting of the
blood. So the same way that's true by a חטאת העוף chatas
ha-of because the תורה Torah says ולא יבדיל, ve-lo yavdil, so אף
כאן af kan here too אף כאן כשהוא אוחז הראש בגוף מזה.
af kan keshe-hu ochez ha-rosh ba-guf mazeh.
Here
too when he holds the head through the body the head and
the body are still connected when he is doing the squirting even
by an עולת העוף. olas ha-of. So therefore they are more connected,
the body and the head. Now he presumably would not argue on
the fact that when you do the actual הקטרה, haktarah, the burning,
you fully sever it. But at least at the time here when
they are actually doing the squirting and when the מליקה melikah took
place, he says the two are more connected, likely are connected by
the חטאת העוף. chatas ha-of. That's רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון. Rabbi Elazar
b'Rabbi Shimon. So the גמרא Gemara continues and says, one minute, מה
להלן בסימן אחד אף כאן בסימן אחד, mah lehalan be-siman echad af
kan be-siman echad, as long as you're comparing them, why not go
the whole way and say the same way by a חטאת העוף
chatas ha-of it's only one סימן siman because it says ולא יבדיל,
ve-lo yavdil, you're specifically not supposed to really sever. So therefore you
only cut one of the סימנים. simanim. Here too for an עולת
העוף, olas ha-of, let's really go the whole distance and say the
same way like a חטאת chatas only one סימן. siman. תלמוד לומר
והקריבו. talmud lomar ve-hikrivo.
No, he agrees that when it says by the עולת העוף olas
ha-of you shall offer it, that that means that its offering is
distinct from that of a חטאת העוף chatas ha-of and is not
fully the same. And because again of this comparison of ומלק והקטיר
u-malak ve-hiktir
that does tell you that there is more severing that goes on
by an עולת העוף. olas ha-of. So he, רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון,
Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon, is trying to sort of dance in this
middle ground. On the one hand he does admit that it's more
severed than a חטאת העוף chatas ha-of and on the other hand
it is compared to a חטאת העוף. chatas ha-of. So his compromise
is that the two סימנים simanim are still somewhat connected at the
bottom. And therefore more severed but still the head and the body
are connected.
I have a question.
Yeah, yeah. When it says ולא יבדיל, ve-lo yavdil, when
it says ושיסע אותו בכנפיו ולא יבדיל, ve-shissa oso bichnafav ve-lo yavdil,
right?
Which means to me it doesn't sound like
מליקה melikah but that's just tearing it from the back once you've
already in two.
Well I'm not sure why you would have assumed ולא יבדיל ve-lo
yavdil means a different type of separating but all I can tell
you is that חז"ל Chazal understood that since it's oh I'm sorry
you're saying because it says ושיסע אותו
בכנפיו
ולא יבדיל.
ve-shissa oso bichnafav ve-lo
yavdil.
But doesn't it also say ומלק את ראשו ממול ערפו ולא יבדיל?
u-malak es rosho mimul orfo ve-lo yavdil?
It says ומלק את ראשו ממול ערפו ולא יבדיל. u-malak es rosho
mimul orfo ve-lo yavdil. Okay.
So it says ולא יבדיל ve-lo yavdil by the מליקה. melikah. Yeah
check it out. Yeah it would I think it's right there in
ויקרא Vayikra by the חטאת העוף. chatas ha-of. I think it's ומלק
את ראשו ממול ערפו ולא
יבדיל, u-malak es rosho mimul orfo ve-lo yavdil, pretty sure right there
in ויקרא. Vayikra. Okay, okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay. לתנא קמא. le-Tanna Kamma. So now let's go back to the
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma who says that you do fully sever the
two סימנים. simanim.
Since you learn from ומלק והקטיר u-malak ve-hiktir that the body and
the head are separate when they're being burnt, so therefore they should
be severed in the act of מליקה Melika by an עולת העוף.
Olat Ha'of. והקריבו למה לי? Vehikrivo lama li?
Why did the Torah have to explicitly sort of separate out the
offering of the עולת העוף Olat Ha'of from the חטאת העוף? Chatat
Ha'of? If you learned specifically from verses by an עולת העוף Olat
Ha'of that the head and the body are severed the same way
they're burned separately, they're severed in the מליקה, Melika, why did you
need an extra פסוק pasuk to underscore that it's not like a
חטאת העוף? Chatat Ha'of? You just internally from עולת העוף Olat Ha'of
you learned that there's this severing going on. Why do you need
the פסוק pasuk to underscore that it's different from a חטאת העוף?
Chatat Ha'of? So did you find the פסוק, pasuk, Michael?
No, I have it here, ויקרא... Vayikra...
No, no, no, it's not there, it's ויקרא ה' Vayikra Hei I
said because that's where you have a חטאת העוף. Chatat Ha'of. Let's
look at the end of ויקרא. Vayikra.
Where are we? Not there, stay there... Yeah. והקריבו הכהן אל המזבח
ומלק את ראשו והקטיר המזבחה ונמצה דמו על קיר
המזבח.
Vehikrivo hakohen el hamizbei'ach umalak es rosho vehiktir hamizbei'acha venimtza
damo al kir hamizbei'ach.
Okay,
so anyway, so why do you need
והקריבו Vehikrivo that separates out the חטאת העוף Chatat Ha'of from the
עולה, Olah, והקריבו? Vehikrivo? So now the גמרא Gemara says אי לאו
והקריבו, Ei lav Vehikrivo, had it not said והקריבו, Vehikrivo, הוה אמינא
hava amina I would have thought מה כמשפט, mah kemishpat, כמשפט חטאת
העוף, kemishpat Chatat Ha'of, because I would have said no, that because
the Torah says you shall do like this עולת העוף כמשפט, Olat
Ha'of kemishpat, I would have said like actually רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון
Rabbi Elazar b'Rebbi Shimon does read it, that it means you should
compare it more to a חטאת העוף Chatat Ha'of and you should
maybe say it's more connected. ואי משום ומלק והקטיר, Ve-ei mishum umalak
vehiktir,
and what about the fact that I learn from the verse that
it says do מליקה Melika and burn, that that means the same
way the burning of the head and body are separately the מליקה
Melika have to fully sever? So how could I have gone ahead
and learned from a חטאת העוף? Chatat Ha'of? No, I could have
gotten out of it. הוה אמינא hava amina I would have said
מה הקטרה בראשו של מזבח, mah haktara be-rosho shel mizbei'ach, this is
a different ראש, rosh, the same way you burn at the top
of the altar, obviously you can't put the stuff on the fire
from the bottom of the altar, you have to be at the
top of the altar to put the stuff on the fire, so
the same way that's true, אף מליקה בראשו של מזבח, Af melika
be-rosho shel mizbei'ach, you have to do מליקה Melika at the top
of the altar. What does this mean? Because a bird חטאת Chatat
you do מליקה Melika at the bottom. You do the מליקה Melika
and you squirt the blood at the bottom of the altar. A
bird עולה Olah you do at the top of the altar. How
do I know that? Because of the juxtaposition of ומלק והקטיר, umalak
vehiktir, that you do מליקה Melika and burn, which it says by
the bird עולה. Olah. So the same way you obviously burn you
have to be by the fire, by the top, when you do
מליקה Melika you have to be by the fire as well. Actually
it's interesting to note, and this is a way to remember too,
that the birds are exactly the opposite of the animals. By the
animals we know, I mean, the חטאת Chatat is at the
top, relatively easy to remember because the חטאת Chatat is special that
you apply the blood with the finger at the corners of the
altar, at the horns of the altar, so you have to be
at the top, everything that's not a חטאת Chatat is at the
bottom. And the birds are reversed, that the חטאת Chatat is at
the bottom and the עולה Olah is at the top. So he
said like this, I needed והקריבו Vehikrivo to tell me don't treat
it like a חטאת העוף, Chatat Ha'of, because if it wouldn't have
been that, I would have been inclined based on the words כמשפט
kemishpat to say like a חטאת העוף, Chatat Ha'of, don't fully sever
the head. And the fact that there's this פסוק pasuk about מליקה
Melika and burning, I wouldn't have learned it to teach me sever
the head the same way it's severed during burning, I would have
taught a different thing, that you do the מליקה Melika at the
top of the מזבח. mizbei'ach. So I have to first start with
freeing myself from the חטאת, Chatat, from the association of the עולה
Olah to the חטאת. Chatat. Once I'm freed from that association of
comparing the two bird sacrifices, then I will be able to learn
that the עולה Olah is fully severed. Okay, that's what the תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma says. Okay, השתא דכתב רחמנא והקריבו, Hashta de-ksav rachamana
Vehikrivo, and now that the Torah says you shall bring it, which
sort of, you know, severs, yeah, if we're talking about severing, we're
separating the עולת העוף Olat Ha'of from the חטאת העוף Chatat Ha'of
and does not force that association, so I'm not pulled to say
that the head has to be like the חטאת העוף. Chatat Ha'of.
So therefore, דריש ביה נמי הא, darish beih nami ha, I'm free
to also make the other דרשה, drasha, I'm free to learn now
from the juxtaposition of the מליקה Melika and the burning that the
same way... I learn out both things. I learn out the same
way the burning is at the top, the מליקה Melika is at
the top of the מזבח. mizbei'ach. And I also learn out that
the same way you burn the head and the body separately, you
do the מליקה Melika of the head and the body separately. Okay,
fine, so that's what we're saying. So again, the תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma says the basic issue, sort of the crux of the issue
is how you interpret ויעשה כמשפט, ve-ya'aseh kemishpat, do it like the
law, which is said by the עולת העוף. Olat Ha'of. If you
start by linking that to the חטאת העוף Chatat Ha'of which comes
with it in the קרבן, korban, then you're going to say that
it has to... the head has to be more connected to the
body. If you're going to basically say no, it's not referring to
the חטאת העוף Chatat Ha'of at all, it's referring to the חטאת
בהמה, chatat behema, referring to some other קרבן, korban, then you are
freer to say that the head... the way you treat the severing
of the head is more fundamentally different and you more fully sever
the head from the body. דוב? Dov?
Just want to go here now, but it seems that we're taking
great pains to say that whatever we do for animals is completely
different from what we do for birds. You just said it's just
the opposite. And how come in terms of כשרות kashrus we essentially
treat them the same?
First of all, I don't know if we're taking great pains, it's
just a point that I pointed out that it's the reverse of
the
עולה.
Olah. No, making whatever's כשר kasher for... Right. No, I know, but
then how come by the time, you know, we get to like
בשר וחלב basar v'chalav issues, you essentially treat them the same, don't
we?
Well, the emphasis here is not to contrast a bird קרבן korban
from an animal קרבן. korban. The emphasis of the... I mean, that
was just a small point I made about the location on the
מזבח. mizbe'ach. Okay? The emphasis of the משנה mishnah is to contrast
מליקה melikah to שחיטה. shechitah. Okay? So שחיטה shechitah is not birds
versus animals. It's שחיטה shechitah when I want to eat the meat
and it's equal to birds and animals. Okay?
But we do שחיטה shechitah for עוף, of, we're okay with one
סימן, siman, but for animals we do two.
Yes, but that's not what we're discussing.
No, I know. I'm just asking. Okay. I don't know if you
want to talk about it at some point, but I'm just curious
then how come by the time we get to like בשר וחלב
basar v'chalav issues, you essentially treat them...
Not really. First of all, there's some that say there's not even
any דרבנן derabbanan by birds. There's a position of רבי יוסי הגלילי
Rabbi Yosi HaGelili that says you can eat birds with milk.
And we follow that?
No, obviously, but... but at most we follow it דרבנן. miderabbanan. Okay?
So anyway, we'll worry about it when we get to things that
you see as not being consistent. Okay, fine. So now the גמרא
Gemara goes on to say like this. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says הא חטאת בהמה דגמרינן מחולין מנלן, ha chattat behemah degamrinan mechullin
menalan, and so what did the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma do with
comparison to the עולת העוף, olat ha-of, because it wasn't being compared
to a bird חטאת, chattat, it was being compared to a bird
עולה. olah. So where do we know this from? So אמר רב
חסדא דאמר קרא, amar Rav Chisda de'amar kra, the פסוק pasuk says...
I'm sorry, so I'm sorry, did I misspeak? A bird עולה olah
was not being compared to a bird חטאת, chattat, it was being
compared to an animal חטאת. chattat. What do we learn from the
comparison to an animal חטאת? chattat? So there was a list of
things we learned. One of those is that it could only come
from חולין chullin money, from non-מעשר ma'aser money. Although you can use
your מעשר שני ma'aser sheni money to bring a free-will קרבן korban
because the whole point of the מעשר שני ma'aser sheni money is
eaten in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So as long as I'm bringing a free-will
קרבן korban and I'm going to eat the קרבן, korban, I'm eating
it in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. You cannot use that money to bring an
obligatory קרבן. korban. You cannot... you cannot exempt yourself from your obligations
through מעשר ma'aser money, money that's already earmarked for something else. So
now the גמרא Gemara says, so where do we know this from
by a בהמה behemah that I can now apply it to a
bird? אמר רב חסדא דאמר קרא, amar Rav Chisda de'amar kra, the
פסוק pasuk says והקריב אהרן את פר החטאת אשר לו. vehikriv Aharon
et par hachattat asher lo. Aaron shall bring the sin offering that
is his. So this is by יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. So right,
remember that the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol brings into the בית המקדש
Beit HaMikdash on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, he brings his cow and
he brings the goat of the people and he does the whole
וידוי viduy and the sprinkling, etc. So why does it say אשר
לו? asher lo? משלו ולא משל ציבור. mishelo velo mishel tzibbur. It
has to be out of his own, right? Well, I'll get to
that in a minute. It has to be out of his own
pocket. He has to pay for it
and not communal funds. ולא משל מעשר, velo mishel ma'aser, and not
out of any other funds, not out of any
מעשר ma'aser funds.
But he'd give it to himself. Why wouldn't he be able to
do מעשר? ma'aser?
That is exactly my point. The only reason the מעשר ma'aser is
a question is because you could, in terms of the normal assumptions
of מעשר, ma'aser, use the money and eat the food in ירושלים.
Yerushalayim. So you could buy a קרבן korban and eat the meat
in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So although you would be satisfying those criteria, the
whole point of saying and not משל מעשר mishel ma'aser is a
different issue. Although you will be using the money to be eating
something in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, you cannot sort of exempt yourself from another
obligation with מעשר ma'aser money. That's the concern.
We're saying this is a paradigm for אהרן. Aharon. What? We're taking
this as a paradigm for the case by אהרן. Aharon. Yes, because
he wouldn't be doing מעשר ma'aser at
all. Why not? In ירושלים? Yerushalayim? I mean, like he was in
the מדבר. midbar.
Oh, okay, right, right. So we're assuming אהרן Aharon here is not...
right, correct, there was no מעשר ma'aser yet by that time. Yes,
אהרן Aharon here is a model for all כהנים גדולים. Kohanim Gedolim.
Okay, fine.
Okay, now going back to Michael's other question, which is how do
you necessarily learn that the law that applies to אהרן Aharon applies
to other חטאות, chata'ot, you know, and applies in general? I mean,
obviously maybe יום כיפור Yom Kippur has special criteria. So תוספות Tosafot
asks that question, and תוספות Tosafot has a brilliant answer. He says
no, obviously the פסוק pasuk has to be coming to teach about
more than just יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Because what happens with the
פר החטאת par hachattat of יום כיפור? Yom Kippur? What... what did
you do with it after you sprinkled the blood? What happened to
the meat? You burned it. So of course you can't use מעשר
ma'aser money for it, because you only can use מעשר ma'aser money
if you're going to eat the meat. Right? That's the only
precedent about מעשר ma'aser money is by a קרבן korban that the
meat is going to be eaten. There was never a question that
you couldn't use מעשר ma'aser money for an עולה. olah. The only
question was can I use מעשר ma'aser money for like a חטאת
chattat or שלמים shelamim where I'll eat the meat, but I'm exempting
myself from an obligation. So therefore, since the פסוק pasuk wouldn't have
to tell me this by the case of אהרן Aharon by the
חטאת chattat because it's burnt anyway, therefore we're going to assume that
it's telling me a law that applies to all קרבנות korbanot or
at least all חטאות chata'ot and not necessarily just that of אהרן.
Aharon.
And once
we say that, then we link the bird עולה olah to the
animal חטאת, chattat, we learn to apply it to bird sacrifices as
well.
So you can use מעשר ma'aser for your עולות, olot, is what
you're saying, according to... No, you...
you can't. You don't even need a פסוק pasuk for that because
the meat isn't being eaten. The only thing in the end you
can use מעשר ma'aser for is for a free-will sacrifice that you
have not priorly... previously obligated yourself in. If I said הרי עלי
שלמים, harei alai shelamim, now I have an obligation to bring a
שלמים, shelamim, now I can't use my מעשר ma'aser money because I
have a standing obligation that I'm exempting myself from. But if I
take my מעשר ma'aser money and I say זה לשלמי, zeh leshalmai,
right, or that I can
do. Well not the בעלים, ba'alim, by the כהנים. kohanim. So that
is interesting. You wouldn't eat it but you know you can give
your שלמים shlomim meat to other people to eat. Right. And my,
that's what I meant. I meant you can give your מעשר ma'aser
right money for other people to eat. So yes. But the most
obvious uses of מעשר ma'aser money in a קרבן korban would be
in a שלמים shlamim case.
None of it was, none of the edible parts were burned on
the מזבח? mizbeach?
No, I mean, you know, some of the inners, הקרב, hakeirev, הכרעים,
hakrayim, whatever. Right, so I guess the question would be is that
would that be like a, you know, would that be considered like
a waste of some מעשר ma'aser money that some part of it
is not being used?
Or I mean what if for example you're allowed to use מעשר
ma'aser money, you're allowed to sort of buy the bottle together with
the wine, you know, as an example by the מעשר ma'aser money.
You can buy let's say I don't know I could buy a
pomegranate with the מעשר ma'aser money although eighty percent of the pomegranate
is the rind. So I assume it would have been some analogy
based on that. I don't in general I don't think that we
assume that these things that are put on the altar normal people
would have eaten anyway. Okay. So now, okay, so now it goes
on. Let's take a look.
Okay, so one thing we learned to apply from an animal חטאת
chatas to a bird עולה olah was you can only use it
from
non-מעשר ma'aser money. Okay. Now, ביום, bayom, so the other thing we
learned is that it has to be brought at the day because
we learn also that a חטאת chatas is brought at the day
possibly from even the case of אהרן Aharon as well. Because it
says ביום הזה. bayom hazeh. So the same way חטאת chatas is
brought during the day, a bird עולה olah is also brought during
the day. So the גמרא Gemara says
ביום, bayom, מביום צוותו נפקא. mibayom tzivoso nafka. We learn it from
a general פסוק pasuk that applies to all קרבנות. korbanos. It says,
you
know, זאת התורה לעלה ולמנחה ולחטאת ולמלואים zos hatorah l'olah ul'mincha ul'chatas
ul'miluim etc. ביום צוותו את בני ישראל להקריב את קרבניהם. bayom tzivoso
es b'nei Yisrael l'hakriv es korbanaihem. On the day he commanded, God
commanded the children of Israel to bring their קרבנות. korbanos. So it's
a general פסוק pasuk that applies to all קרבנות korbanos and says
on the day God commanded from which we learn not only that
God happened to command it on a particular day but that the
bringing of them occur during the daytime. So you don't need to
learn it from a חטאת, chatas, we learn straight from this verse
that every קרבן korban is at the daytime. So the גמרא Gemara
says okay, כדי נסבה, kidi nasba, that was just thrown in for
naught. You know we're listing things not every one of them do
we really need to learn now from a חטאת. chatas. Okay, what
else did it say we learned out from a חטאת chatas to
apply to a bird עולה? olah? ידו הימנית. yado hayemanis. That you
the same way by a חטאת chatas the כהן kohen uses his
right hand. Okay, that there, you know, and there a number of
times it says that the כהן kohen shall take from his right
hand ולקח הכהן
באצבעו הימנית, v'lakach hakohen b'etzba'o hayemanis, specifically, especially when it's talking about
things like the מצורע metzora and the putting on the body of
the מצורע metzora to purify him etc. So therefore we learn the
same way those are with his right hand, here too by an
עולה olah the כהן kohen uses his right hand in the עבודה.
avodah. And here particularly let's say in the מליקה melika you do
it with your right hand as well. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says that again you don't need to learn it out from a
חטאת. chatas. מדרבה בר בר חנה נפקא. mide'rabba bar bar Chana nafka.
You learn it from the general teaching of רבה בר בר חנה.
Rabba Bar Bar Chana. דאמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר ריש לקיש,
de'amar Rabba Bar Bar Chana amar Reish Lakish, because רבה בר בר
חנה Rabba Bar Bar Chana said, and he didn't say that ten
times fast, in the name of ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, כל מקום
שנאמר אצבע או כהונה, kol makom shene'emar etzba o kehuna,
whenever the תורה Torah talking about how to bring sacrifices mentions either
a finger or a כהונה, kehuna, which is probably pretty almost always
going to mention כהונה, kehuna, אינו אלא ימין. eino ela yamin.
It's implicit that you use the right hand of the כהן. kohen.
Because since one place the תורה Torah speaks again by the מצורע
metzora it says ולקח הכהן באצבעו הימנית, v'lakach hakohen b'etzba'o hayemanis,
so with his right finger, so we learn out that any one
of those words signals the right, either the word כהן kohen or
the word אצבע. etzba. So once we learned that out then it
says obviously כהן kohen by מליקה melika so obviously it means his
right. So therefore why do I need to learn out from the
bird עולה olah learn that out from the חטאת? chatas? I just
learned it out from the use of the word כהן kohen that
it's his right hand.
Maybe הני מילי? hanei mile?
Because that's what the גמרא's Gemara going to say. So ואידך, v'idach,
so what would the response be?
כהונה בעיא אצבע, kehuna ba'ia etzba, אצבע לא בעיא כהונה. etzba lo
ba'ia kehuna. No, when it says כהן kohen it still doesn't mean
right hand. Right is only when the תורה Torah uses the word
finger. Finger signifies right finger and right hand. But if it says
the word כהן kohen it would still need to say the word
finger to indicate right. אצבע, etzba, it's true if it does say
the word finger לא בעיא כהונה lo ba'ia kehuna it does not
have to say the word כהן. kohen. So no we don't we
can't just assume always right
hand. We can only assume right hand if the תורה Torah says
אצבע etzba and therefore we do have to learn out from the
חטאת chatas this principle of right hand. And therefore at least by
birds what it certainly emphasizes is not only that the squirting gets
done with the right hand but the מליקה melika itself gets done
with right hand which to remind you led to the fascinating question
of תוספות Tosafos of whether the גמרא Gemara was serious whether the
כהן kohen could actually use his teeth to do מליקה. melika. Because
the only way we know that the כהן kohen uses his fingernail
is because it says בעצמו של כהן. b'atzmo shel kohen. The דרשה
drasha is בעצמו של כהן. b'atzmo shel kohen. There's never a דרשה
drasha specifically about the thumb or the finger. The דרשה drasha is
it says the כהן kohen does מליקה melika with the כהן's kohen
body himself he does מליקה. melika. So that led to
תוספות. Tosafos. Okay so that’s how we know you need the right
hand, we do learn it out from חטאת, Chatas, you can't learn
it out directly. ותנא קמא דרבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון ממול עורף מנא
להו? V’tanna kamma d’Rabbi Elazar
b’Rebbi Shimon mi-mul oreph minalhu?
Finally it says okay, רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon, if not רבי שמעון,
Rebbi Shimon, רבי ישמעאל Rebbi Yishmael linked the bird עולה Olah to
the bird חטאת Chatas to teach me that מליקה Melikah comes from
the back of the neck, which it says explicitly by the bird
חטאת, Chatas, it does not say by the bird עולה. Olah. So
where does... where does תנא קמא ורבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Tanna kamma
v’Rabbi Elazar b’Rebbi Shimon learn this idea that מליקה Melikah comes from
the back of the neck? So גמרי מליקה ממליקה. Gamri melikah mi-melikah.
Okay, they don't learn it because it says כמשפט kemishpat and that
links the bird חטאת Chatas and the bird עולה. Olah. They learn
it from the verb, מליקה. melikah. By both of them it says
מליקה, melikah, and one of them it describes מליקה melikah from the
back of the neck, so therefore מליקה melikah will always mean from
the back of the neck. Okay, so the upshot of all of
this is that because remember although we had that fascinating discussion of
נבילה neveilah and the moment of death, etc., our משנה mishnah got
around to talking about מליקה. melikah. We are now digressing a little,
right, because we're saying שחיטה's shechitah from this part, מליקה's melikah from
that part, and now we're moving off our topic of שחיטה shechitah
and talking about מליקה. melikah. So one of the things that we're
focusing on right now is, so A, מליקה melikah was from the
back of the neck through the spinal cord, through the neck bone.
So first that led to a very interesting discussion about when is
something considered dead if the neck is cut before the trachea and
the esophagus and so on, and now it's leading to the technical
issue about whether מליקה, melikah, how מליקה's melikah different for a bird
חטאת chatas and a bird עולה. olah. Bird חטאת, chatas, the תורה
Torah says ולא יבדיל, velo yavdil, so you only cut one סימן.
siman. A bird עולה, olah, because here it’s separated from a bird
חטאת chatas by והקריבו, v’hikrivo, and that we learn out from a
פסוק pasuk that talks about burning the head and the body separately,
מליקה melikah also is a fuller severing of the body and the
head. Debate of the רבנן ורבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון, rabbanan v’Rabbi Elazar
b’Rebbi Shimon, the רבנן rabbanan say a full severing of both סימנים
simanim although not literally cutting the head completely off, and רבי אלעזר
ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar b’Rebbi Shimon says no it's still somewhat similar
to a bird חטאת chatas and therefore you don't fully sever both
סימנים, simanim, they both remain a little bit connected so it somewhat
is connected to the body. Now we're going to turn for the
rest of this פרק perek
to continued digressions, because if you remember our משנה mishnah by comparing
where you do the שחיטה shechitah and where you do the מליקה
melikah said, so it turns out where the שחיטה's shechitah good for,
the מליקה's melikah not good for. שחיטה's shechitah from the front and
the sides, מליקה melikah is only in the back. And what a
מליקה's melikah good for, the שחיטה's shechitah not good for. מליקה melikah
can only be the back and שחיטה, shechitah, right, so they're exactly
what they're called mutually exclusive categories. Okay, שחיטה's shechitah front and sides,
מליקה's melikah back, you cannot... you can’t do מליקה melikah from the
front, you can’t do the שחיטה shechitah from the back. That's going
to lead out to a series of משניות mishnayos where something says
what's good for A is not good for B and what's good
for B is not good for A. So let's take a look.
Okay. כשר בתורין פסול בבני יונה. Kasher b’sorin pasul b’vnei yonah.
So this is not talking about שחיטה shechitah anymore, right? The תורה
Torah says that when you bring various bird sacrifices you can bring
either תורין torin or בני יונה. bnei yonah. So בני יונה bnei
yonah are turtledoves, תורין torin is like I think what, something like
pigeons? Somebody can look in their English, I think תור tor is
basically is usually
described as a pigeon. What do you have there, Rifka? Latin. Latin.
Turtledoves and pigeons.
Pigeons. Okay. ותורין v’torin are turtledoves?
בני יונה bnei yonah are pigeons?
No, it's the opposite.
A יונה yonah is a dove, so בני יונה bnei yonah are
turtledoves, which means a baby dove.
It should be pigeons and turtledoves. תורין Torin are turtledoves. Really? That's
crazy.
What is acceptable in case of turtledoves is unacceptable in case of
pigeons. So... תורין torin are turtledoves. Yeah. Wait a minute. That's how...
which one's which? Look up JPS. Which one's which for pigeons? Pigeons
are בני יונה. bnei yonah. Streptopelia turtur. That helps. There you go.
All right. So JPS, let's see what JPS says. Do you run
across pigeons when you see them on the street? Streptopelia whatever. Let
me try. JPS has turtledoves, what’s the order in the פסוק? pasuk?
מן התורים או מן בני היונה? min ha-torim o min bnei ha-yonah?
Is that it? ויקרא Vayikra 1:14. 1:14. I assume. ושיר השירים v’Shir
HaShirim the קול התור kol ha-tor נשמע בארצנו. nishmah b’artzeinu. Not so
the pigeons, which dwell permanently in the land. Yeah, I stand corrected.
Both... everybody here says that תור tor is turtledove and בני יונה
bnei yonah is pigeon. Okay, I always assumed that turtledove meant a
small... a small dove. I looked... I looked at the JPS... this
and this and this and this, both of these have that as
well. Okay, all right. Let's back to this. So anyway, the גמרא
Gemara assumes and משנה Mishna
assume that the use of the word בני יונה Bnei Yona means
that they are small, young. Okay?
Because the word children. So, כשר בתור, Kashar BiTor, the תורה Torah
says you can bring turtle doves and pigeons. So what's good for
turtle doves means that when the animal is at its adult stage,
פסול בבני יונה, pasul BiBnei Yona, that's not good for the baby,
the young pigeons.
Pigeons are only good when they are בני, bnei, when they are
young. So they have to be in the immature stage. כשר בבני
יונה, Kashar BiBnei Yona, what's good for pigeons, which is immature, פסול
בתורין pasul BiTorin is invalid for the turtle doves, they have to
be in the adult age. תחילת הציהוב בזה ובזה פסול. Techilas HaTziuv
Bizeh Uvizeh pasul. Now when the, when the, apparently, the neck feathers,
when it's in its teenage years, when it starts, when it's between
being young and being adult, its neck feathers start to turn like
a little yellowish or golden, and
the beginning of
the gold turning of the neck feathers is invalid for both. It's
not young enough to be considered בני, bnei, to be considered a
child, and it's not old enough to be considered an adult.
Okay, so that's invalid for both. So these categories as
opposed to
the שחיטה Shechita and מליקה Melika where they completely were the entire
spectrum,
one was A and one
was not A, this is A and B and you have the
excluded middle.
You have children and adult, and you have the middle case which
satisfies neither, which is this issue of like, if you would, you
know, the teenage years, sort of the בר מצוה... bar mitzvah... exactly,
we're going to get to that. Good call. Okay, so let's see
what the גמרא Gemara says. תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: תורין, Torin, turtle
doves, גדולים, gedolim, means adults, גדולים כשרים, gedolim kesherim, adults are kosher,
קטנים פסולים, ketanim pesulim, the children, the, you know, young ones are
invalid. בני יונה, Bnei Yona, the opposite is true by the pigeons
or the young pigeons. קטנים כשרים, ketanim kesherim, young ones are valid,
immature ones, גדולים, gedolim, adults, פסולים, pesulim, are invalid. נמצא כשר בתורין
פסול בבני יונה כשר בבני יונה פסול בתורין. Nimtza kashar biTorin pasul
biBnei Yona, kashar biBnei Yona pasul biTorin. What's good for one is
not good for the other and vice versa. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan.
It can't be our pigeon, our pigeons don't get like a gold,
a gold thing. I didn't see baby pigeons. I don't know, have
you ever seen a baby pigeon? How do you know? Oh, you're
just saying they don't retain it when they're older.
Yeah, I don't know. דב Dov is looking up in the Wikipedia.
Yes, it doesn't have anything yet about this. About the ages and
how they change over as they mature. Okay. Is this for offerings?
This is for קרבנות. korbanot. Any time the תורה Torah speaks about
a bird קרבן, korban, it always says either a תור tor or
בני יונה. bnei yona. What about your regular eating? It's not talking...
no, no, not eating at all. This is no longer anything to
do with חולין. chullin. It has to do with the structure of
what's kosher for A is not kosher for B, what's kosher for
B is not kosher for A, and just random things that we're
throwing into this discussion. Okay, so this is specifically for קרבנות. korbanot.
תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: תורין גדולים ולא קטנים. Torin gedolim velo ketanim.
תור Tor means adults and not children. שיכול ולא דינו? Sheyachol velo
dinu? I might have made a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. What would
the קל וחומר kal vachomer have been? ומה בני יונה שלא הוכשרו
בגדולים... Uma bnei yona shelo huchsharu bigdolim... so it always does these
things, right? Rather than assuming that each thing is a specific category,
we'll make a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. If that category works for
that one, it should certainly work for the other. So what's the
story by בני יונה? bnei yona? The young pigeons. The young pigeons.
I still don't get how יונה yona means a pigeon, anyway. Okay.
שלא הוכשרו בגדולים הוכשרו בקטנים. shelo huchsharu bigdolim huchsharu biktanim. Those have
to be young, they're not good as adults, they're only good as
children. So if that's true, תורין, torin, when it comes to the
תור, tor, שהוכשרו בגדולים, shehuchsharu bigdolim, that adults are good, אינו דין
שיוכשרו בקטנים? eno din sheyuchsharu biktanim? קל וחומר Kal vachomer that the
young, that the children should be good, right? A little crazy. One
says adults, the other says children. Let's make a קל וחומר. kal
vachomer. If for that one it's only children and not adults, this
where it's even adults certainly should also include children. Part of what
makes this קל וחומר kal vachomer somewhat possible is that תור tor
might not exclude the idea of children. בני יונה Bnei yona emphasize
the idea that young. תור Tor might be a generic and might
include both young and adult. Okay, yeah.
I see רש"י Rashi on the
משנה Mishna that says לא תורין. lo torin. Now what רש"י Rashi
is I think bothered with is that it's not a... yeah, that
was an interesting רש"י. Rashi. I think he's because it's not תורים,
torim, which is the מ mem in the תורה. Torah. Well, maybe
he's kind of hinting that in other places it doesn't mean what
it means here.
No, I don't think so. I think he just means that it's...
although it's saying כשר בתורין, kashar biTorin, but it's not the right
word in the תורה. Torah. The תורה's Torah word is
תורים torim with a
מ mem
and this is תורין torin with a ן. nun. That's all I
think רש"י Rashi is saying. All right, anyway, so I might have
made a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. So תורין שהוכשרו בגדולים, torin shehuchsharu
bigdolim, תור tor which is good with an adult, אינו דין שיוכשרו
בקטן? eno din sheyuchsharu bikatan? Certainly it should be good with a
קטן.
katan. Oh, you know what we need to look at?
We need to look at what's-his-name, Felix, in his חי במקרא. Chai
BaMikra. Okay, anyway. תלמוד לומר: Talmud lomar: so the verse teaches: תורין
גדולים ולא קטנים. Torin gedolim velo ketanim. תור Tor adults, it means
only adults, not minors. The גמרא's Gemara going
to ask how do you know, where
do you see from the פסוק pasuk to exclude
קטנים, ketanim, to exclude young ones? בני יו Bnei yo Now we're
going to look at the other one. בני יונה, Bnei Yona, so
what do we say about these pigeons?
קטנים ולא גדולים,
Ketanim velo Gedolim, only the young ones, not the adults. שיכול והלא
דין הוא, She-yachol ve-halo din hu, I could make a קל וחומר.
Kal Vachomer. ומה תורים שלא הוכשרו בקטנים הוכשרו בגדולים, U-ma torim she-lo
huchsharu b'ketanim huchsharu b'gedolim, you just got through saying that a תור
Tor
is only an
adult and not a young one, so בני יונה שהוכשרו בקטנים, Bnei
Yona she-huchsharu b'ketanim, בני יונה, Bnei Yona,
the pigeons, that
the young ones are kosher, אינו דין שיוכשרו בגדולים,
Eino
din she-yuchsharu
b'gedolim, certainly the
adults should be, again one of those crazy קל וחומרס, Kal Vachomers,
right?
Why should we assume קל וחומר? Kal Vachomer? Why don't we just
assume they're distinct categories? But okay, I might have made such a
קל וחומר. Kal Vachomer. If תור Tor is only adults, and בני
יונה Bnei Yona are big children, maybe I should read it to
mean even children, and certainly adults, קל וחומר Kal Vachomer adults. תלמוד
לומר, Talmud
Lomar,
בני יונה, Bnei Yona, so therefore the Torah says בני יונה, Bnei
Yona,
קטנים
ולא גדולים, Ketanim velo Gedolim, only the young ones, not the adults.
Now, besides that it was a crazy הוה אמינא Hava Amina of
a קל וחומר, Kal Vachomer, how do we get from the verse
to be mutually exclusive categories? Where do you read in the פסוק
Pasuk that it means and it's really two questions. One question is
how do you know תור Tor does not mean generic, adult or
children? That's one question. The other question is, right, that presumably the
way רש"י Rashi framed it is, you know, by קרבנות, Korbanot, we
normally need the Torah to repeat something to tell you that if
you don't do this, it's no good. So where do we see
that it's דווקא, Davka, that it's מעכב, Me'akev, that it has to
be only adults in one and only young ones in the other?
So that's what the גמרא Gemara says. מאי תלמודא, Mai Talmuda, what's
the learning? Where do you get any of these ideas from the
verses to be so exclusive and to read תור Tor as only
adults? So אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so רבא Rava says, לא לישתמיט
קרא ליכתוב מן בני התורים או מן היונה. Lo lishtameit kra lichtov
min bnei hatorim o min hayona. The Torah never sort of what?
The verse, right, the verse never, you know, gives an example of
ever saying the opposite. You'll never find any verse that says בני
תורים Bnei Torim or that says יונה. Yona. The verses are completely
consistent, so basically it's an argument from silence. And the way רש"י
Rashi says it, there are so many verses that talk about bird
sacrifices and it always says בני יונה Bnei Yona and תור Tor
and never reverses it, from that we should infer that it's דווקא
Davka and that תור Tor does not mean adult and that בני
יונה Bnei Yona means only... תור Tor does not include children and
בני יונה Bnei Yona means only children and that they are exactly
the categories that they are described and nothing more, nothing less. So
that's what רש"י Rashi said, now that by the way is an
important phrase, תוספות Tosafot says it would have we would have said
that even if there had not been a lot of verses, even
if there had been only just one verse, the fact that it
did not say it in a way that could have suggested, you
know, to be bigger categories. But anyway, this is very important because
this gets to the old question of making arguments from silence. You
know, and the old point is that they say like, lack of
evidence isn't evidence. Okay, so on the one hand lack of evidence
isn't evidence unless that, you know, it's a circumstance in which if
it were true you would have you know there was all reason
to have thought that there something there would have been some evidence
and there isn't. So there are some cases context-dependent on when the
fact that something isn't there can also be significant. So sometimes when
you find that in הלכה Halakha people try to argue from silence
and often this will come like somebody will make like an absurd
claim like somebody will say oh well like I don't know although
אמירה לגוי Amira l'Goy is not you can't do it on שבת,
Shabbos, if you're standing on your head you can do it because
that's a שינוי. Shinuy. So let's say a פוסק Posek said that,
right? So where you gonna prove it? Where does it say in
the גמרא Gemara that if you're standing on your head it's not
מותר? Muttar? So the argument will be, right, you're not going to
have a direct proof that look it says here somebody was standing
on his head and it still wasn't allowed. The point is it
never says anywhere that this is okay for 2,000 years, it's never
suggested anywhere in הלכה Halakha literature that it makes a difference if
you're standing on your head. So that's an argument, or actually a
rebuttal from silence. Where you would have expected if this were true
that it would have appeared somewhere. So that's when you hear that,
the phrase is לא לישתמיט, Lo lishtameit, right, which again I don't
even know the exact translation of this idiomatic expression but sometimes it's
לא לישתמיט קרא, Lo lishtameit kra, the פסוק Pasuk would not have
let it go without ever having said it, or לא לישתמיט תנא,
Lo lishtameit Tanna, so you know the תנא Tanna would never have
been absent from the משניות, Mishnayot, or לא לישתמיט שום פוסק, Lo
lishtameit shum Posek, no פוסק Posek would have ever you know it
never would have you know that wouldn't have said this if it
were not if it were the case. So that's actually an important
phrase that's used from an argument from silence. If this were true,
it would have appeared somewhere in our last 2,000 years of הלכה
Halakha literature. Okay, so just think of how many questions I'm really
asking you when I'm being fly. There you go, okay. So anyway,
that's a very important idiomatic expression which comes up in you know
in issues of as I said הלכה Halakha you know about arguing
from silence. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: אימא
בני יונה דכתב רחמנא בני קטנים אין גדולים לא. Eima bnei yona
d'chtav Rachmana bnei ketanim in gedolim lo. So now the גמרא Gemara
really asks what I was sort of getting to before. Okay, it
has to be exactly as the word means but what do we
know what the word means? Maybe בני יונה Bnei Yona means just
קטנים Ketanim because that's the word בני, Bnei, just immature ones, but
תורים Torim when it says תור, Tor, which is again what do
we say turtledove, איבעיא גדולים ליי... Iba gedolim lai... If you want
you can bring adults, if you want you can bring even the
even the immature ones. So the גמרא Gemara says no, דומיא דבני
יונה. Dumiya de-bnei yona. No, because we make a parallel to בני
יונה. Bnei Yona. מה בני יונה קטנים ולא גדולים, Ma bnei yona
ktanim velo gedolim, the same way בני יונה Bnei Yona means only
the קטנים ktanim and not the adults, אף תורים גדולים ולא קטנים,
Af torim gedolim velo ktanim, so תור Tor also means the opposite
category. The way רש״י Rashi says it is it's sort of echoing
the idea of our משנה. Mishna. The same way בני יונה Bnei
Yona means what's good for בני יונה Bnei Yona cannot use the
category of תור, Tor, what's good for תור Tor does not work
for בני יונה. Bnei Yona. בני יונה Bnei Yona can only be
can only be immature, the same is true in the reverse. תור
Tor cannot use the category of בני יונה, Bnei Yona, so therefore
immature cannot work for תור. Tor. Now by the way, when we
say can't work, don't get confused, it doesn't mean that they're the
same, I mean as we had a whole discussion, they're not the
same species, but we mean that age group cannot work. So the
same way for בני יונה Bnei Yona it's only the age group
of young and not adult, so we're going to assume the you
know parallel reverse by the תור, Tor, it's only the adult's age
group not the young age group. Okay. And this assumes this sort
of begs the question. I understand. Okay, תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, we
taught a ברייתא, Braita, יכול, Yachol, it's possible, יהיו כל התורים וכל
בני היונה כשרים. Yiyu kol ha-torim ve-chol bnei ha-yona kshairim. Maybe again
sort of repeating, all תורים Torim and all בני יונה Bnei Yona
would be כשר. Kasher. מעתה, Me-ata, here what it really does not
mean is all, here what it really means is this this sort
of teenagers, what's the other word, that's I'm just being facetious, adolescents,
thank you. Maybe it's the adolescent years, okay? So how do you
know that this sort of gray zone or gold zone, right, in
the middle, how do you know that it's not good? Maybe that
counts as young, it also counts as adult? Maybe rather than saying
it's excluded from both, maybe it should be included in both categories.
So maybe all the things that fall under youth and all the
things that fall under adult, even these middle years, should be okay.
תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, the verse teaches, מן התורים, Min ha-torim, you
shall take from the turtle doves, ולא כל התורים, Velo kol ha-torim,
not everything that you might have suggested falls in that category, not
everything that you might have wanted to call an adult. So these
this adolescence is not acceptable. Similarly, מן בני היונה, Min bnei ha-yona,
from the בני יונה, Bnei Yona, ולא כל בני היונה, Velo kol
bnei ha-yona, not everything that you would have said would have fallen
in that category. So not everything you could have argued was a
child, not the age of adolescence. So the word מן Min is
sort of saying a narrower definition of the category. The narrow definition
of adulthood, the narrow definition of being a child, so the middle
cases, the adolescent, the golden feathers, right, that is excluded because those
don't fall in the narrow definitions of youth or adulthood. Okay, ולא
כל בני, Velo kol bnei, פרט, Prat, which excludes, לתחלת הציהוב שבזה
ושבזה שפסול, Le-tchilat ha-tziuv she-be-ze ve-she-be-ze she-pasul, the beginning of the getting
golden of the feathers in both categories, which are invalid, too old
to be a child, not old enough to be an adult. Okay,
the constant anguish of the adolescent. Alright, so מאימתי תורים כשרים? Me-eimatai
torim kshairim? So when are the תור Tor going to be good?
If the beginning of getting the feathers gold isn't good? משיזהיבו, Mi-she-yazhivu,
when not just the beginning to get golden, it starts turning a
little yellowish, but when it actually turns its fully golden state, that's
when it's considered an adult. Again, I don't know if we're really
talking about what we call pigeons, I agree with Michael, whoever saw
pigeons with gold feathers by their by their neck feathers? Maybe we're
talking about something else, maybe we're talking about other species of pigeons.
What does Wikipedia tell you? That baby pigeons are duller and don't
have the richer color like they do when they're adults. Ah. Is
that what they mean by gold? Maybe gold but it just means
the richer color of the various colors in the plumage, and yeah,
there's some yellow. Okay, very nice. There you go. So when that
color fully turn, then it's an adult. Is it yellow or just
around the neck? The גמרא, Gemara, רש״י Rashi constantly talks about the
neck feathers. The גמרא Gemara isn't spelling that out. The גמרא Gemara
is just talking about יצהיבו. yatzhivu. Right. Right. We don't know which
species it's talking about. Okay. Alright, so therefore, so when those colors
fully turn, then it's an adult. Okay, מאימתי בני יונה פסולים? Me-eimatai
bnei yona psulim? Now when are the בני יונה Bnei Yona invalid?
Well, we already know the answer, what age they're no longer considered
children. משיצהיבו, Mi-she-yatzhivu, when they begin to get... It's interesting here, you
know it says יצהיבו yatzhivu rather than יזהיבו. yazhivu. צהב Tzahav and
זהב, zahav, presumably it's suggesting by the different verbs because it doesn't
say when it begins to get get get yellow as opposed to
when it finishes getting yellow. Really the only difference in the in
the language is יזהיבו yazhivu and יצהיבו, yatzhivu, right? המשנה Ha-Mishna says
תחלת הציהוב, tchilat ha-tziuv, but here this ברייתא, Braita, which means the
beginning, but here the ברייתא Braita is only contrasting it with the
verb, זהב zahav and צהב, tzahav, presumably for it צהב tzahav meant
like a beginning of a yellow and זהב zahav meant like a
brighter, you know or deeper yellow. Okay. So that tells us that
age it's already considered to be in the adolescence, not good for
בני יונה. Bnei Yona. Okay. תני יעקב קרחה, Tani Yaakov Karcha, now
יעקב קרחה Yaakov Karcha taught however, what's the other end? When does
it begin to become good? Baby chicks when they're just born are
like, you know, disgusting, they're like all gooky and whatever, you know,
and they so it was obviously we assume not כשר kasher for
a קרבן korban yet. So when will, how old does it have
to be? And there's no הלכה halacha of eight days like there
is by, you know, mammals to wait eight days. So when can
you begin to bring the בני יונה? b'nei yonah? So משיעלו, misheiya'alu,
from משיעלו, misheiya'alu, I don't even know how to pronounce it. Anyway,
from that moment. So what does it mean? הוא תני לה ואמר
לה, hu tanni lah ve'amar lah, he taught the ברייתא braita and
he explained, you know, he had a tradition of the ברייתא braita
but then he explained it on his own, מכי שעם meki she'im
based on the פסוק pasuk in איוב, Iyov, אפרוחיו יעלעו דם. efroachav
ye'ale'u dam. The chicks will יעלעו דם. ye'ale'u dam, Very lovely. What
does the word יעלעו ye'ale'u mean? It's an עולא? Olla? So it
might mean עולה, oleh, right, that the blood more fully flows through
all parts of the body. That's what רש״י Rashi says. עולא Olla
like עולא Olla means עולה, oleh, like you know you pluck a
feather out and blood comes out. Oh, pluck a feather out, blood
comes out. That's interesting, רש״י Rashi didn't say that. תוספות Tosafot has
two possible explanations. What, let's first read the next how the גמרא
Gemara describes it as and then we'll go back to what the
word means. אימתי, eimatai, when is that? אמר אביי Amar Abaye מכי
שמיט גדפא מיניה, meki shamit gadfa minei, from the time its wing
moves from it ואתי דמא, ve'ati dama, and then the blood comes.
So I assume that means when they are little chicks, I don't
know, do people know here about birds? And maybe your English gives
some explanation, I didn't look this up, but I assume you know
that that when they're when they're birds they have more like what,
don't they have like more like little little appendages, it's not yet
wings? Does anybody know this? Does the wings come later? What what
does your English say there about this, Rivka, anything helpful? All kinds
of different interpretations of the word יעלעו. ye'ale'u But what does he
say about אביי's Abaye statement, מכי שמיט גדפא מיניה? meki shamit gadfa
minei? When one pulls a feather and it bleeds. Oh, it's like
you were saying, Michael, I'm sorry, so I totally I misunderstood this.
Okay, very good, oh, I totally misunderstood this. מכי שמיט גדפא מיניה
ואתי דמא, meki shamit gadfa minei ve'ati dama, I see. Okay, my
mistake, when you pull a feather from it and the blood comes
out. I thought okay, don't worry how I was misreading that. Okay,
so therefore, yes? The other interpretation says its young chicks swallow blood.
That's the פשט. pshat. They swallow blood? Like a worm kind of
thing? Interesting. Okay, swallowing a liquid when it's able to swallow liquids.
Aha, okay, I don't know, maybe like liquidy worms or something? So
many interpretations, she probably has no idea. יעלעו ye'ale'u. is almost like
יבלעו. yivle'u. Okay, but anyway, on the topic of of yellowing or
back to that, yes, the תוספות Tosafot says that it appears that
the גמרא Gemara would be talking about just after a few days.
Baby pigeons, they're born with very dull feathers and only after four
or five days they they get more colorful. Really? So we're only
talking about a window of four or five days? Yeah, but then
he says, but the משנה Mishnah in קנים Kinnim seems to be
talking about like already flies, so it doesn't make sense, so he
suggests that maybe it's the eyes, that the eyes after five months
the eyes become brighter or yellower. Okay. All right, there you go.
Even even the eyes and that's what he says? No, it's still
he's saying means the color, but the color where? No, I'm not
saying the color of the eye, you're saying the color of the
eyes? Yeah, the color of the eyes, not the color of the
feathers. Oh, that's interesting. When it has blood and אפרוחיו יעלעו דם.
efroachav ye'ale'u dam. Right, okay, no, no, no, no, no, he's going
back to the color. Okay, so back to this. So thank you,
yeah, I was misreading that, thank you. Okay, so when is it
considered old enough that it's considered fit to bring on the מזבח,
mizbeach, you know, that it's not when it's just born? So it
is משיעלו, misheiya'alu, which now we're saying means that as the blood
comes out if you pluck a feather. So יעלעו ye'ale'u דם, dam.
אימתי eimatai אביי Abaye says מכי שמיט גדפא מיניה ואתי דמא, meki
shamit gadfa minei ve'ati dama, when you pluck a feather, the blood
comes out. Fine. So now we know the age. Now we get
to a fascinating discussion in the גמרא, Gemara, which will be for
the few lines today and for the rest of tomorrow, which is
how do you deal with these middle cases? Are these middle cases
independent categories and, you know, adolescence, you're neither an adult or a
child, it is its own category? Or is it actually it does
fall in one category, we just don't know how to categorize it?
The way the גמרא Gemara calls it is this a ספק safek
or is this a בריה? biryah? Right, you have this actually in
a lot of areas of הלכה. halacha. Things which you don't exactly
know how to categorize and the question is do they define their
own category or are they or is it just we don't know
which category to put them in. One example for, you know, which
is somewhat like the gender example, right, the whole issue about an
אנדרוגינוס, androgynos, a person with both genitals. Are they, you know, are
they their own category or they're either male or female, we just
don't know how to fit it in, or is there something that's,
you know, maybe the world isn't dichotomous in terms of gender? How
about בין השמשות? bein hashmashot? Is בין השמשות bein hashmashot either night
or day, we just don't know which, or we don't know which
part of בין השמשות bein hashmashot is night, which part day, or
is there a med... middle category called dusk, which is neither night
nor day? So this is an obviously a fascinating question that can
be applied in many areas, and the גמרא Gemara is actually going
to apply it in a few areas, not just limited to ours,
but it's going to start with ours. Well this would I think
would either bear what you're saying out or or maybe not, because
we had other areas of קדשים Kodshim where we said לרבות lerabbos
the פלגס, palgas, which in case you would include it here, or
if you say it's really distinct and they're really their own thing,
then you'd say that פלגס. palgas. So we're going to get there.
We're going to see פלגס. palgas. But by the way, it's not
one answer for everything. בין השמשות bein hashmashos might be one idea,
אנדרוגינוס Androgynos might be another idea, ציהויא tzihuya might be, you know,
something else, who knows? The point is that this question about when
something is not, you know, when you've divided the world in a
dichotomous way and something doesn't fall into A or B, so you
keep your dichotomy and just say you don't know which category to
put it in, or does that force you to say things aren't
a dichotomy? And so it could be a different answer for every
case we apply it to. Let's take a look. Okay. Okay, so
בעי רבי זירא, bei Rabi Zeira, רבי זירא Rabi Zeira asked, האומר
הרי עלי עולה מן התורים או מבני היונה והביא תחילת הציהויא שבזה
ושבזה מהו. ha'omer harei alai olah min hatorim o mibnei hayona veheivi
t’chilas hatzihuya shebaze v’shebaze mahu. So let's say a person says, "I
will bring a bird קרבן korban and I'm going to have the
options: either תור tor or בני יונה, bnei yona, either one will
satisfy my vow." And then what he does, he goes and he
brings a תור tor that is at this yellowing stage and a
בני יונה bnei yona that's at this yellowing stage. And he brings
both. Now תוספות Tosafos asks the whole question, "How do we allow
you to bring both since one is definitely פסול?" pasul? But let's
bracket that for a moment. He brings both. Did he satisfy his
vow? If you say that this adolescence is definitely not adult or
child, so he didn't satisfy his vow. He didn't bring a תור
tor that was an adult and he didn't bring a בני יונה
bnei yona that was a child. But if you say it's one
or the other, we just don't know, then one of the animals
was correct. Either it was a child and the בני יונה bnei
yona were good, or this stage is adulthood and the תור tor
is good. So here you have your question: is it one or
the other we don't know, or is it clearly a middle category?
So let's take a look. והביא, veheivi, so he said, "I'm going
to bring either an עולה olah or either a תור tor or
בני יונה, bnei yona, either way I'll satisfy my obligation." והביא תחילת
הציהויא שבזה ושבזה, veheivi t’chilas hatzihuya shebaze v’shebaze, and he brought the
תורים torim and the בני יונה bnei yona that were both in
this stage of adolescence of the beginning of the yellowing. מהו? mahu?
What's the הלכה? halacha? ספיקא הוי? sveika havei? Do we say that
there is, it is, they are either adults or children, we just
don't know which category to put it in? If that's true, ונפיק,
venafik, then you satisfied your obligation because one of the קרבנות korbanos
you brought was right. Either this stage is adulthood and the תור
tor was good, or this stage was childhood and the בני יונה
bnei yona were good. או דילמא בריה הוי ולא נפיק? o dilma
berya havei velo nafik? It's its own animal, its own, meaning not
literally animal, but what phrase do we use? I know category, but
we actually have a phrase like that, right, when we say it's
its own animal, it's its own, don't we have an idiom like
that? Anyway, anyway, what? I'm blanking. Anyway, whatever. Okay. So anyway, he
says, right, it's its own stage, and adolescence is neither one nor
the other, and you did not satisfy your obligation. It was not
a child בני יונה, bnei yona, it was not an adult תור,
tor, it was too adolescent and you did not satisfy your obligation.
ולא נפיק. velo nafik. Okay. אמר רבא, amar Rava, so רבא Rava
says, תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear. פרט לתחילת הציהויא שבזה
ושבזה. prat lit’chilas hatzihuya shebaze v’shebaze. This is sort of what Michael
said: why don't we infer something from the fact that you needed
a פסוק? pasuk? We had a פסוק: pasuk: מן התורים מן בני
היונה min hatorim min bnei hayona to exclude the adolescence stage, שפסול.
shepasul. אי אמרת בשלמא בריה הוי, ei amart bishlamah berya havei, if
you say adolescence is its own state, so therefore שפיר, shapir, you
know you need a פסוק, pasuk, because if it's its own state
you might have thought that maybe it counts for adults or maybe
it counts for child because it's a state that's nearby. So therefore
you needed a פסוק pasuk to exclude it. אלא אי אמרת ספיקא
הוי, ela ei amart sveika havei, if that this is only a
doubt, so whose doubt is it? It's our doubt. So איצטריך קרא
למיעוטי ספיקא? itztrich kra limi’utei sveika? Why would God have to tell
you, "Don't bring something that's a doubt"? If you, as human beings,
you stupid people, have a doubt whether this is considered to be
adulthood or childhood, that's your problem. I told you, "Bring children בני
יונה, bnei yona, adults תור." tor. If you can't figure out what
this is, don't bring it. But the פסוק pasuk doesn't have to
tell you, "Don't bring it if you have a doubt." We already
know you bring things that you know are good, you don't bring
things that are doubtful. So if you need a פסוק, pasuk, obviously
a פסוק pasuk is not telling you how to deal with doubt.
The פסוק pasuk is telling you this is its own category and
it's not acceptable. So the גמרא Gemara says, "You know what? You're
right. Let's just read the answer." You're right. If it's a doubt,
you did not need the פסוק pasuk for that. So the פסוק
pasuk really is teaching something else. כי איצטריך קרא, ki itztrich kra,
the verse would be coming למיעוטי נרבע ונעבד, limi’utei nirva v’neevad, other
things that were wrong with the bird. Not that they were in
the adolescence, that would be just a doubt, that we would know
on our own not to bring. If the bird was, let's say,
used in an act of bestiality or if it was worshipped as
an idol. There the פסוק pasuk is telling you: don't bring all
birds, these birds are not valid. But as the גמרא Gemara will
say later, and I don't want to... was only applied here as
an אסמכתא. asmachta. So basically it's saying you're right, if this is
its own category, you need the verse to exclude adolescents. If it's
just a question of doubt, is this adult or childhood, but it's
definitely one, then you don't need the verse. The reason we quoted
the verse was an אסמכתא asmachta and we really would use the
verse to teach me something else, but the verse would not need
to exclude a ספק, safek, that's our issue, we would figure out
on our own not to bring something that is a ספק. safek.
So we will continue with this tomorrow, and it will extend not
only to this case, but as I said, is fascinating applying to
a number of other areas of is something its own category or
is something we just don't know how to categorize it and could
be asked in many, many cases throughout ש״ס shas and there could
be a different answer in each case.